<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE library PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
  "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % threads.entities SYSTEM "entities.xml">
  %threads.entities;
]>
<section id="thread.acknowledgements"
last-revision="$Date$">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <para>William E. Kempf was the architect, designer, and implementor of 
  &Boost.Threads;.</para>
  <para>Mac OS Carbon implementation written by Mac Murrett.</para>
  <para>Dave Moore provided initial submissions and further comments on the 
  <code>barrier</code>
  and 
  <code>thread_pool</code>
  classes.</para>
  <para>Important contributions were also made by Jeremy Siek (lots of input
  on the design and on the implementation), Alexander Terekhov (lots of input
  on the Win32 implementation, especially in regards to boost::condition, as
  well as a lot of explanation of POSIX behavior), Greg Colvin (lots of input
  on the design), Paul Mclachlan, Thomas Matelich and Iain Hanson (for help
  in trying to get the build to work on other platforms), and Kevin S. Van
  Horn (for several updates/corrections to the documentation).</para>
  <para>Mike Glassford finished changes to &Boost.Threads; that were begun
  by William Kempf and moved them into the main CVS branch.
  He also addressed a number of issues that were brought up on the Boost
  developer's mailing list and provided some additions and changes to the 
  read_write_mutex and related classes.</para>
  <para>The documentation was written by William E. Kempf. Beman Dawes
  provided additional documentation material and editing.
  Mike Glassford finished William Kempf's conversion of the documentation to 
  BoostBook format and added a number of new sections.</para>
  <para>Discussions on the boost.org mailing list were essential in the
  development of &Boost.Threads;
  . As of August 1, 2001, participants included Alan Griffiths, Albrecht
  Fritzsche, Aleksey Gurtovoy, Alexander Terekhov, Andrew Green, Andy Sawyer,
  Asger Alstrup Nielsen, Beman Dawes, Bill Klein, Bill Rutiser, Bill Wade,
  Branko &egrave;ibej, Brent Verner, Craig Henderson, Csaba Szepesvari,
  Dale Peakall, Damian Dixon, Dan Nuffer, Darryl Green, Daryle Walker, David
  Abrahams, David Allan Finch, Dejan Jelovic, Dietmar Kuehl, Douglas Gregor,
  Duncan Harris, Ed Brey, Eric Swanson, Eugene Karpachov, Fabrice Truillot,
  Frank Gerlach, Gary Powell, Gernot Neppert, Geurt Vos, Ghazi Ramadan, Greg
  Colvin, Gregory Seidman, HYS, Iain Hanson, Ian Bruntlett, J Panzer, Jeff
  Garland, Jeff Paquette, Jens Maurer, Jeremy Siek, Jesse Jones, Joe Gottman,
  John (EBo) David, John Bandela, John Maddock, John Max Skaller, John
  Panzer, Jon Jagger , Karl Nelson, Kevlin Henney, KG Chandrasekhar, Levente
  Farkas, Lie-Quan Lee, Lois Goldthwaite, Luis Pedro Coelho, Marc Girod, Mark
  A. Borgerding, Mark Rodgers, Marshall Clow, Matthew Austern, Matthew Hurd,
  Michael D. Crawford, Michael H. Cox , Mike Haller, Miki Jovanovic, Nathan
  Myers, Paul Moore, Pavel Cisler, Peter Dimov, Petr Kocmid, Philip Nash,
  Rainer Deyke, Reid Sweatman, Ross Smith, Scott McCaskill, Shalom Reich,
  Steve Cleary, Steven Kirk, Thomas Holenstein, Thomas Matelich, Trevor
  Perrin, Valentin Bonnard, Vesa Karvonen, Wayne Miller, and William
  Kempf.</para>
  <para>Apologies for anyone inadvertently missed.</para>
</section>

