<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE library PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
  "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % threads.entities SYSTEM "entities.xml">
  %threads.entities;
]>
<section id="threads.faq" last-revision="$Date$">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Are lock objects <link
		linkend="threads.glossary.thread-safe">thread safe</link>?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">No!</emphasis> Lock objects are not meant to
		be shared between threads. They are meant to be short-lived objects
		created on automatic storage within a code block. Any other usage is
		just likely to lead to errors and won't really be of actual benefit anyway.
		Share <link linkend="threads.concepts.mutexes">Mutexes</link>, not
		Locks. For more information see the <link
		linkend="threads.rationale.locks">rationale</link> behind the
		design for lock objects.</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	    <para>Why was &Boost.Threads; modeled after (specific library
		name)?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>It wasn't. &Boost.Threads; was designed from scratch. Extensive
		design discussions involved numerous people representing a wide range of
		experience across many platforms. To ensure portability, the initial
		implements were done in parallel using POSIX Threads and the Win32
		threading API. But the &Boost.Threads; design is very much in the spirit
		of C++, and thus doesn't model such C based APIs.</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Why wasn't &Boost.Threads; modeled after (specific library
	    name)?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
        <para>Existing C++ libraries either seemed dangerous (often failing to
		take advantage of prior art to reduce errors) or had excessive
		dependencies on library components unrelated to threading. Existing C
		libraries couldn't meet our C++ requirements, and were also missing
		certain features. For instance, the WIN32 thread API lacks condition
		variables, even though these are critical for the important Monitor
		pattern &cite.SchmidtStalRohnertBuschmann;.</para>
      </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Why do <link linkend="threads.concepts.mutexes">Mutexes</link>
		have noncopyable semantics?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
        <para>To ensure that <link
		linkend="threads.glossary.deadlock">deadlocks</link> don't occur. The
		only logical form of copy would be to use some sort of shallow copy
		semantics in which multiple mutex objects could refer to the same mutex
		state. This means that if ObjA has a mutex object as part of its state
		and ObjB is copy constructed from it, then when ObjB::foo() locks the
		mutex it has effectively locked ObjA as well. This behavior can result
		in deadlock. Other copy semantics result in similar problems (if you
		think you can prove this to be wrong then supply us with an alternative
		and we'll reconsider).</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>How can you prevent <link
		linkend="threads.glossary.deadlock">deadlock</link> from occurring when
		a thread must lock multiple mutexes?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>Always lock them in the same order. One easy way of doing this is
		to use each mutex's address to determine the order in which they are
		locked. A future &Boost.Threads; concept may wrap this pattern up in a
		reusable class.</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Don't noncopyable <link
		linkend="threads.concepts.mutexes">Mutex</link> semantics mean that a
		class with a mutex member will be noncopyable as well?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>No, but what it does mean is that the compiler can't generate a
		copy constructor and assignment operator, so they will have to be coded
		explicitly. This is a <emphasis role="bold">good thing</emphasis>,
		however, since the compiler generated operations would not be <link
		linkend="threads.glossary.thread-safe">thread-safe</link>. The following
		is a simple example of a class with copyable semantics and internal
        synchronization through a mutex member.</para>
<programlisting>
class counter
{
public:
   // Doesn't need synchronization since there can be no references to *this
   // until after it's constructed!
   explicit counter(int initial_value)
      : m_value(initial_value)
   {
   }
   // We only need to synchronize other for the same reason we don't have to
   // synchronize on construction!
   counter(const counter&amp; other)
   {
      boost::mutex::scoped_lock scoped_lock(other.m_mutex);
      m_value = other.m_value;
   }
   // For assignment we need to synchronize both objects!
   const counter&amp; operator=(const counter&amp; other)
   {
      if (this == &amp;other)
         return *this;
      boost::mutex::scoped_lock lock1(&amp;m_mutex &lt; &amp;other.m_mutex ? m_mutex : other.m_mutex);
      boost::mutex::scoped_lock lock2(&amp;m_mutex &gt; &amp;other.m_mutex ? m_mutex : other.m_mutex);
      m_value = other.m_value;
      return *this;
   }
   int value() const
   {
      boost::mutex::scoped_lock scoped_lock(m_mutex);
      return m_value;
   }
   int increment()
   {
      boost::mutex::scoped_lock scoped_lock(m_mutex);
      return ++m_value;
   }
private:
   mutable boost::mutex m_mutex;
   int m_value;
};
</programlisting>
      </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>How can you lock a <link
		linkend="threads.concepts.mutexes">Mutex</link> member in a const member
		function, in order to implement the Monitor Pattern?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>The Monitor Pattern &cite.SchmidtStalRohnertBuschmann; mutex
		should simply be declared as mutable. See the example code above. The
		internal state of mutex types could have been made mutable, with all
		lock calls made via const functions, but this does a poor job of
		documenting the actual semantics (and in fact would be incorrect since
		the logical state of a locked mutex clearly differs from the logical
		state of an unlocked mutex). Declaring a mutex member as mutable clearly
		documents the intended semantics.</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Why supply <classname>boost::condition</classname> variables rather than
		event variables?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>Condition variables result in user code much less prone to <link
		linkend="threads.glossary.race-condition">race conditions</link> than
		event variables. See <xref linkend="threads.rationale.events" /> 
		for analysis. Also see &cite.Hoare74; and &cite.SchmidtStalRohnertBuschmann;.
		</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Why isn't thread cancellation or termination provided?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>There's a valid need for thread termination, so at some point
		&Boost.Threads; probably will include it, but only after we can find a
		truly safe (and portable) mechanism for this concept.</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Is it safe for threads to share automatic storage duration (stack)
		objects via pointers or references?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>Only if you can guarantee that the lifetime of the stack object
		will not end while other threads might still access the object. Thus the
		safest practice is to avoid sharing stack objects, particularly in
		designs where threads are created and destroyed dynamically. Restrict
		sharing of stack objects to simple designs with very clear and
		unchanging function and thread lifetimes. (Suggested by Darryl
		Green).</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
	<qandaentry>
	  <question>
	    <para>Why has class semaphore disappeared?</para>
	  </question>
	  <answer>
	    <para>Semaphore was removed as too error prone. The same effect can be
		achieved with greater safety by the combination of a mutex and a
		condition variable.</para>
	  </answer>
	</qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</section>
